{"tossups": [{"question": "One of this ruler\u2019s sons was murdered in the arms of this ruler\u2019s wife, Julia Domna. This emperor died in Eboracum while campaigning in Scotland. At the second century Battle of Issus, this leader defeated one of his rivals, Pescennius [pesk-EHN-ee-uss] Niger. This man emerged victorious from the Year of the Five Emperors. His son Geta was killed by his other son and successor Caracalla. For 10 points, identify this Roman emperor from 193 to 211 and founder of the Severan dynasty.", "answer": "<b><u>Septimius Severus</u></b> [prompt on <b><u>Severus</u></b>]  [Max Schin<u>dler]</u>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "This singer quoted Khrushchev\u2019s line \u201cWe will bury you!\u201d and hoped the title people \u201clove  their children too\u201d in his song \u201cRussians\u201d. He performed alongside Branford Marsalis and Phil Collins at Live Aid in 1985. More famously, he joined Andy Summers and Stewart Copeland in a band for which he sang a song inspired by Nabokov\u2019s <em>Lolita</em> called \u201cDon\u2019t Stand So Close To  Me.\u201d For 10 points, name this man who wrote \u201cMessage in a Bottle\u201d for the band in which he was lead singer, The Police.", "answer": "<b><u>Sting</u></b> [or Gordon (Matthew Thomas) <b><u>Sumner</u></b>]  [Rob Carso<u>n]</u>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "Participants in this uprising gathered at Braddock\u2019s Field and Parkinson's Ferry. It began when members of a local \u201cDemocratic Society\u201d burned John Neville\u2019s home. This rebellion was sparked by an excise tax levied by Alexander Hamilton, and put down by a militia led by Virginia governor \u201cLight-Horse Harry\u201d Lee and President George Washington. For 10 points, name this 1794 rebellion in Pennsylvania named for an alcoholic beverage.", "answer": "<b><u>Whiskey</u></b> Rebellion  [Saul Hanki<u>n]</u>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The death of Mary appears in the middle of one of these works in Poland by Veit Stoss [VAYT stohs]. Saint Margaret holds a book and stands on top of a dragon on the right side one of these works by Hugo van der Goes. Saint Cecilia plays the organ in one of these works featuring an enthroned figure flanked by John the Baptist and Mary, which was commissioned by the artist's brother Hubert. For 10 points, name these works of art, one of which was painted by Jan Van Eyck and named for Ghent.", "answer": "<b><u>altarpiece</u></b>s [prompt on <b><u>polyptych</u></b>s]  [Chris Man<u>ners]</u>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "This person was appointed to an Industrial Commission by then-Governor Al Smith and served as head of the New York Consumer's League. This person was succeeded by Lewis Schwellenbach after spending a record length of time in that role. Her accomplishments include founding the precursor to OSHA, chairing the 1935 Committee on Economic Security and fighting for legislation to regulate wages and hours for employees. For 10 points, name this Secretary of Labor under FDR, the first female cabinet member.", "answer": "Frances <b><u>Perkins</u> </b> [Zeke Berdichevsky<u>]</u>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This person first came to power under the tutelage of Concino Concini, who was killed due to the influence of Charles de Luynes. He led the attempt to capture La Rochelle, making  Huguenots sign the Peace of Alais. He was the target of the Day of the Dupes, when Marie de Medici attempted to have him removed. He led the French cause in the Thirty Years War and was replaced by Mazarin after his death. For 10 points, name this cardinal who advised Louis XIII.", "answer": "Cardinal <b><u>Richelieu</u> </b> [Jason Zhou]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "An effect named for this scientist concerns the rotation of the plane of polarization of light in matter upon the application of magnetic field. His motor used a magnetic field to rotate a current-carrying wire resting on a pool of mercury. An object enclosed by a conductor is unperturbed by external electric fields, and hence rests in a cage named for this man. For 10 points, name this physicist, who started his career as an apprentice to Humphry Davy and discovered a law of electromagnetic induction.", "answer": "Michael <b><u>Faraday</u> </b> [Sriram Pendyala]", "metadata": "Science - Physics"}, {"question": "A philosopher from this country contended that reality had been replaced entirely by symbols and signs in the book <em>Simulacra and Simulation</em>. Jurgen Habermas discussed the 9/11 attacks in a series of dialogues on terrorism with a philosopher from this country. That philosopher from this country described ten \"plagues\" of capitalism in <em>Specters of Marx</em> and discussed <em>diff\u00e9rance</em> in the book <em>Of Grammatology</em>. For 10 points, name this country where deconstructionism was founded by Jacques Derrida.", "answer": "<b><u>France</u></b> [or the <b><u>French</u></b> Republic; or R\u00e9publique <b><u>fran\u00e7aise</u></b>] [Chris Man<u>ners]</u>", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "This country\u2019s Kagera Salient was invaded in 1978 by a neighbor. John Okello led an uprising that united the clove-producing Pemba Island with this country, which has been ruled solely by the Chama Cha Mapinduzi Party since independence. The concept of \"Ujamaa\" was promulgated in the Arusha Declaration, which called for African Socialism in this country. For 10 points, identify this East African country led after independence by Julius Nyerere, whose largest city is Dar es Salaam.", "answer": "<b><u>Tanzania</u></b> [or United Republic of <b><u>Tanzania</u></b>; or Jamhuri ya Muungano wa <b><u>Tanzania</u></b>] [Chris Chie<u>go]</u>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A provisional government led by this man was ended by an 1870 expedition led by Garnet Wolseley, and he later took a seat in parliament despite being an outlaw on the run. This man ordered the execution of Thomas Scott, and was himself was captured and executed for treason by the government of John A. Macdonald following a defeat at the battle of Batoche. For 10 points, name this Metis leader of the Red River and Northwest rebellions in Canada.", "answer": "Louis David <b><u>Riel</u> </b> [Zihan Zheng -ed. Patric<u>k Lia</u>o]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This ruler\u2019s wedding was preceded by a failed assassination attempt against Gaspard de Coligny, and this ruler gained a decisive victory at the battle of Ivry over the Duke of Mayenne and the Catholic League. This ruler was assassinated by Francois Ravaillac, though he survived the St. Bartholomew\u2019s Day massacre. After repeated failed sieges of Paris, he gained the throne by converting to Catholicism. For 10 points, name this victor of the War of the Three Henries, the first French king from the House of Bourbon.", "answer": "<b><u>Henry IV</u></b> of France [or <b><u>Henry</u></b> III <b><u>of Navarre</u></b>; do not accept \u201cHenry III\u201d alone]  H<u>enry IV iss</u>ued this edict <u>grantin</u>g re<u>ligious tole</u>rance to Huguenots in 1598. It was later overturned by the Edict of Fontainebleau. ANSWER: Edict of <b><u>Nantes</u> </b> [Zihan Zheng]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A woman led an uprising against this ruler that culminated in the Battle of the Camel. While praying, this man was mortally wounded by the poisoned sword of a Kharijite assassin. This ruler\u2019s son is the subject of the holiday of Ashura, which celebrates his martyrdom. This  successor of Uthman was the final of the four \u201cRightly Guided\u201d caliphs. For 10 points, name this  father of Husayn, the first legitimate caliph according to Shi\u2019a Muslims.", "answer": "<b><u>Ali</u></b> ibn Abi Taib", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {}, {"question": "This man supported the mayoral campaign of George Moscone, leading to his appointment as chairman of the San Francisco Housing Committee. People loyal to this man assassinated Congressman Leo Ryan, after which he laced barrels of Flavor-Aid with cyanide. For 10 points,  name this leader of the People\u2019s Temple whose followers committed mass suicide in Guyana.", "answer": "Jim <b><u>Jones</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "One member of this group drew a map of the world while in the service of the Wanli Emperor. An influential member of this order is the dedicatee of the Novena of Grace and preached in Goa and Japan. Those two men are Matteo Ricci and Frances Xavier. The founder of this order was wounded at the Siege of Pamplona and wrote <em>The Spiritual Exercises</em>. For 10 points, name this religious order founded by Ignatius of Loyola.", "answer": "<b><u>Jesuit</u></b>s [or <b><u>Society of Jesus</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "In October 2014, the city of Derna in this country was occupied by militant members of ISIS. The losing side in the elections of 2014 in this country rejected the results, beginning its second civil war in three years. As a result, the elected government of this country was forced to flee to Tobruk from its capital of Tripoli. For 10 points, name this North African state that was ruled by Muammar al-Gaddafi.", "answer": "<b><u>Libya</u></b> [or the State of <b><u>Libya</u></b>; or Awanak n <b><u>Libya</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "Like Hassler Whitney, this man\u2019s work in algebraic geometry produced a namesake embedding theorem. This man lends his name to situations where no agent is better off if they are the only one to change their strategy. With Harsanyi and Selten, this mathematician won the 1994 Econ Nobel for his work in game theory. For 10 points, identify this schizophrenic subject of the movie <em>A Beautiful Mind.</em>", "answer": "John Forbes <b><u>Nash</u></b>, Jr.", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Economics"}, {}, {"question": "This city was briefly led by Robert Courtenay. The Treaty of Viterbo ended a period in which this city was controlled by the Latin Empire. The city of Zara was attacked prior to this city in a campaign led by Enrico Dandolo. For 10 points, name this home of the Golden Horn, a city sacked during the Fourth Crusade that was the the capital city of the Byzantine Empire.", "answer": "<b><u>Constantinople</u></b> [or <b><u>Istanbul</u></b>; prompt on \u201c<b><u>Byzantium</u></b>\u201d]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This law was used to deny permits for mailing Father Coughlin's newsletter <em>Social</em> <em>Justice</em>. Amendments to this act were used to deport anarchist Emma Goldman. The phrase \"clear and present danger\" was used in <em>Schenck v. U.S.</em> as a rationale for upholding this law's constitutionality. In recent years, it has been used against Chelsea Manning and Edward Snowden. For 10 points, identify this act intended to prevent its namesake crime of delivering information to enemies of the U.S.", "answer": "<b><u>Espionage</u></b> Act of 1917 [accept, but do not otherwise reveal, <b><u>Sedition</u></b> Act of 1918 before \"Che<u>lsea\"]</u>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>The bull</u> </b><em><b><u>Cum Nimis Absurdum</u> </b></em><b><u>created one of these places that was subject to the</u></b>  <b><u>flooding of the Tiber. A famous family took its name from the \u201cred shield\u201d hanging above</u></b>  <b><u>their house in one of these places. The common name for these places derives from the area</u></b> <b><u>around a foundry in</u><u> (+) Venice. During World War II, Jurgen Stroop burnt one of these</u> <u>places to crush an (*</u>)</b> uprising of prisoners bound for Treblinka. Residents of these places were often obliged to wear yellow clothing. For 10 points, name these districts to which Jews were confined in medieval Europe.", "answer": "Jewish <b><u>ghettos</u> </b> [Bollinger]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>During his years in England, this man published</u> </b><em><b><u>A Treatise on the Improvement of Canal</u></b></em> <em><b><u>Na</u></b><b><u>vigation</u></b></em><b><u>. His contemporary rivals included Oliver Evans, whose designs were deployed</u></b> <b><u>in Western (+)</u><u> waters</u></b><u>.</u><b><u> A protege of Benjamin West, this painter-turned-engineer designe</u>d <u>a proto-subma</u>rine called the </b><em><b>Nautilus</b></em><b> that brought him to the attention of his partner (*) </b>Robert Livingston. He used a design from Boulton and Watt to propel his launch of the <em>Clermont</em> on the Hudson River. For 10 points, identify this American founder of the first successful steamboat venture.", "answer": "Robert <b><u>Fulton</u> </b> [Zeke Berdichevsk<u>y]</u>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>One victim of this event lent her name to the nonprofit Rachel\u2019s Challenge. Cassie</u></b>  <b><u>Bernall allegedly answered \u201cYes\u201d when she was asked if she believed in God by the</u></b>  <b><u>perpetrators of this event, who were mistakenly described as members of the</u> (+) </b> \u201c<b><u>Trenchcoat Mafia\u201d and who killed themselves in a library. An anti-gun doc</u>umentary directed by (*)</b> Michael Moore was titled <em>Bowling for</em> [this event]. For 10 points, name this 1997 event in which Eric Harris and Dylan Klebold killed 12 students and a teacher at a high school in Colorado.", "answer": "<b><u>Columbine</u></b> High School massacre/shooting/etc. [Robert Chu]", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "<b><u>This object\u2019s advantages were mitigated after a specimen was found on Akutan in the</u></b> <b><u>Ale</u><u>utian Islands, and the Thach Weave was another countermeasure developed against i</u><u>t.</u></b> <b><u>This</u><u> (+) vehicle often traveled alongside the G4M \u201cBetty\u201d and was designed to replace the</u></b> <b>A5M \u201cClaude.\u201d The protagonist of Miyazaki\u2019s </b><em><b>The</b></em><b> (*)</b><em>Wind Rises</em> is most famous for designing this object, which was often launched from ships like the <em>Hiryu</em> and <em>Akagi</em>. For 10 points, identify this Mitsubishi-produced WWII-era Japanese fighter plane.", "answer": "Mitsubishi A6M <b><u>Zero</u></b> [accept <b><u>Reisen</u></b> or <b>\u201c<u>Zeke</u>\u201d</b>]  [Robert Chu]", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>A chapter of this book describes the \"inexhaustible entertainment\" of its author's</u></b> <b><u>sur</u><u>roundings while hoeing his bean field. A poem by Thomas Carew ends a chapter</u> <u>of this</u></b> <b><u>book that includes a meticulous list of its author's</u><u> (+) expenditures. This book's author</u> <u>proposes the \"realometer\" in its chapter \"Where</u> I (*)</b> Lived, and What I Lived For.\" The author of this book stressed \"economy\" and \"self-sufficiency\" while living on the land of his friend Ralph Waldo Emerson. For 10 points, name this memoir written by the transcendentalist Henry David Thoreau.", "answer": "<em><b><u>Walden</u></b>; or, Life in the Woods</em>  [Manners]", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "<b><u>A ruler of this house was troubled by the Tour de Nesle affair and lost the Battle of</u></b> <b><u>Go</u><u>lden Spurs. That ruler ordered Jacques de Molay burned at the stake and oversaw</u><u> the</u></b> <b><u>papacy\u2019s move to (+)</u><u> Avignon. The Albigensian Crusade occurred during this house's rul</u>e. This dynasty\u2019s founder succeeded Louis V, the last (*)</b> Carolingian king. It included Philip IV and the canonized Louis IX, and it preceded the House of Valois. For 10 points, name this French ruling house founded by a man named Hugh.", "answer": "House of <b><u>Capet</u></b> [or <b><u>Capetian</u></b> Dynasty]  [Kenji Golimlim]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>A photograph from this book depicts three young boys sleeping on a barrel, and it</u></b> <b><u>derives its title from a line in Rabelais\u2019</u> </b><em><b><u>Gargantua and Pantagruel</u></b></em><b><u>. The then-recent</u></b> <b><u>invention of flash photography allowed this book\u2019s creator to capture the (+)</u><u> poorl</u>y-lit <u>places documented in this book, and its last chapter claims that</u>New York\u2019s \u201ctremendous, ever swelling(*)</b> crowd of wage earners\u201d is \u201cnot housed decently.\u201d For 10 points, name this Jacob Riis book that exposed poor living conditions in urban tenements.", "answer": "<em><b><u>How the Other Half Lives</u> </b></em> [Robert Chu<u>]</u>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Photography"}, {"question": "<b><u>One member of this movement supported both the White Feather movement and a</u></b> <b><u>un</u><u>iversal draft. Earlier, that member of this group aided in the smashing of H.H.</u><u> (+)</u> <u>Asquith's windows.</u><u>This movement organized the Mud March, and was targeted</u> by the Cat and Mouse Acts. This movement accomplished its main goals with the passing of the 1918 (*) </b>Representation of the People Act and the 1928 Equal Franchise Act. For 10 points, name this movement headed by leaders such as Christabel and Emmeline Pankhurst.", "answer": "<b><u>women</u></b>\u2019s <b><u>suffrage</u></b> movement in the United Kingdom [accept clear synonyms and equivalents, like \u201cthe campaign for <b><u>women</u></b>\u2019s right to <b><u>vote</u></b>]  [Laurence Li]", "metadata": "History - American History"}], "bonuses": []}